<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The further vindication, &amp;c. of Mr. Owen consider'd in a letter to a friend</title>
            <author>Gipps, Thomas, d. 1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G779A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213345</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834737</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834737</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39246</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39246)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1793:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The further vindication, &amp;c. of Mr. Owen consider'd in a letter to a friend</title>
                  <author>Gipps, Thomas, d. 1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Gipps.</note>
                  <note>Caption title; imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to Owen, James.  A further vindication of the dissenters from the Rector of Bury's unjust accusations.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Owen, James, 1654-1706. --  Further vindication of the dissenters from the Rector of Bury's unjust accusations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:39246:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39246:1"/>
            <head>THE
Further Vindication, &amp;c.
OF
Mr. Owen
Conſider'd in a LETTER to a Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to your Commands, I ſend you here a
ſhort Account of my Thoughts concerning Mr. <hi>O</hi>'s
<hi>Further Vindication,</hi> &amp;c. In the way of Writing he
has taken up, he is not (I believe) to be parallel'd,
having out-done all Men living a Bar and half, except
haply two or three of the United Brethren, who have
ſufficiently expos'd Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and Father <hi>Alſop.</hi> I ſhall
not ſo much as endeavour to requite him,<note place="margin">Prov. 26. 4. <hi>R. R.</hi>
               </note> being oblig'd
to the contrary, and having already engag'd my ſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
by Promiſe, which I will religiouſly obſerve. For which
Reaſon you muſt not expect here a particular Anſwer, or
that I ſhould follow him ſtep by ſtep: <hi>My</hi> Work then as
well as <hi>Yours</hi> would be endleſs, and it would be difficult
for me not to retort ſome of his ill Language, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
many of his Miſrepreſentations or Miſtakes, which he
is not capable of enduring, nor you willing to be troubl'd
with. All my Deſign, and I ſuppoſe your expectation is,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39246:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that the whole Argument be laid plain and open unto the
view of any one of common Senſe. This I propoſe to my
ſelf to do in the Order of the Sermon, and as briefly as
I can.</p>
            <p>And firſt you muſt remember, that Mr. <hi>De Laune</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely
tax'd the Church of <hi>England</hi> as guilty of diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
from the Word of God, by leaving out the <hi>Titles</hi> of
the Pſalms in our Liturgy Tranſlation; and that I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took
the defence of this Omiſſion, firſt from the uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of the <hi>Titles</hi> being Canonical. Now I ſubmit it to your
Judgment or any obſervant Reader's weighing the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
on both ſides, as they are to be found in <hi>Rem.</hi> and
in <hi>R's</hi> on <hi>R's,</hi> whether Mr. <hi>O.</hi> (who is Mr. <hi>D</hi>'s Vindicator)
has given a convincing Proof of the <hi>Certainty</hi> of the <hi>Titles</hi>
being Canonical: I ſay, this is ſubmitted to your Judgment
without more ado. This notwithſtanding I ſhall here have
occaſion to repeat ſome things, and obſerve others <hi>de novo,</hi>
which will miniſter ſome further ſatisfaction in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted
Point.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>O.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vind. p.</note> has not ſtuck to pronounce me <hi>a Blaſphemer,</hi> and
to give me words of <hi>Braſs,</hi> becauſe I affirm'd, <hi>many of the
Titles were to no purpoſe at all;</hi> nay, he will not allow that
my ſuppos'd Ignorance can make any Attonement for me,
tho' <hi>God himſelf winked at the times of Ignorance.</hi> But let us
look back unto the Rector's obvious meaning. Mr. <hi>D.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
that the <hi>Titles</hi> unfolded the Myſteries of the Pſalms;
the Rector deny'd that they ſerve to any ſuch purpoſe at
all.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. R.</hi> p. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Ex. gr. A Pſalm, a Song,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe <hi>Titles</hi> unlock
no Myſteries that I know of, and if they muſt needs be
call'd Keys they want Wards. Other <hi>Titles</hi> are infinitely
more Myſterious than the Pſalms themſelves. It cannot
be thought the Holy Ghoſt meant to give us them as Keys
to open the ſecret Senſe of the Pſalms; that would be to
explain <hi>obſcurum per obſcurius,</hi> which I am perſwaded the
Spirit of God would never have done. When Jeſus Chriſt
expounded his Parables, he made 'em clear as the Sun.
Beſides, whereas the Myſteries of the Goſpel are confirm'd
out of an abundance of Paſſages in the Pſalms, I do not
find one <hi>Title</hi> brought to prove any one Myſtery, tho' in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
ſome Fathers (who delighted, <hi>Ludere campo Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:39246:2"/>
as <hi>Jerom</hi> ſpeaks) took a liberty to find out I know
not what Myſteries in the <hi>Titles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. R.</hi> p. 13.</note> I pleaded formerly that the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe,
the <hi>Syriack, Arabick,</hi> and the <hi>LXX</hi> Verſion gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
us'd by the Helleniſtical Jews, and the Chriſtians for
ſeveral Ages differ much from the <hi>Hebrew;</hi> that <hi>Gregory
Nyſſen</hi> obſerv'd there was not an intire Agreement between
the Chriſtians and the Jews about the <hi>Titles,</hi> eſpecially of
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, &amp;c. That this Father aſſerts not the
Divine Authority of the <hi>Titles</hi> but Eccleſiaſtical Cuſtom.
By the way note, that Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has declin'd giving any ſort
of Anſwer to this Teſtimony of <hi>Nyſſen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Synop. Crit.</note> I add, <hi>Grotius</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd
<hi>Moſes</hi> was not the Pen man of the <hi>90th.</hi> Pſal. <hi>Eben
Ezra</hi> affirms the <hi>6th. Pſal.</hi> was compos'd (not by <hi>David,</hi>
as the <hi>Title</hi> has it, but) in the Captivity by ſome other
Perſon. Doth it not follow hence, that according to the
judgment of theſe Churches, and theſe Authors, the <hi>Titles</hi>
are not Canonical, at leaſt not certainly ſo? And are <hi>they</hi>
to be all damn'd for ſo many Blaſphemers? It might have
ſuffic'd Mr. <hi>O.</hi> to have let alone the charge of <hi>Blaſphemy</hi>
(which I fancy is a little too much) and to have contented
himſelf with ranking me among Dunces, tho' at the ſame
time you ſee I have ſome not contemptible Company.</p>
            <p>I do not know any better way to clear this Matter than
by conſidering the <hi>Titles</hi> of the ſeveral Books of Scripture,
ſome whereof are moſt certainly not Canonical, not one of
a certainty ſuch, and ſome doubtful. The firſt Section of
<hi>Moſes</hi>'s Pentateuch is in Hebrew call'd <hi>Bereſith,</hi> but in the
LXX, <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and in our Engliſh Tranſlation, <hi>The firſt Book
of Moſes called Geneſis:</hi> Are we, Diſſenters and all, yea and
all Chriſtendom Blaſphemers for departing from the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew?</hi>
The truth is, I do not believe the Author of the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateuch
divided his Work into Five Sections or Books; but
the Church of the Jews, who for convenience intituled each
Section from the firſt word of it, tho' the LXX more judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly
from the principal deſign and matter contain'd in
thoſe Sections. I prefer the <hi>Title</hi> of the LXX to that of
the <hi>Heb.</hi> in the Hiſtorical part of the Kings. In <hi>Heb.</hi> we
find <hi>the Firſt and Second Book of Samuel,</hi> in the LXX more
properly and truly call'd <hi>the Firſt and Second Book of Kings.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39246:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Samuel</hi> died, <hi>1. Sam.</hi> 25. The reſt of this and the next Book
was not (neither could be) written by <hi>Samuel,</hi> nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
him, but the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (and <hi>Samuel</hi> himſelf
is I conceive comprehended in <hi>Kings)</hi> being the Supreme
Judge;) The <hi>Heb.</hi> divides the Pſalter into Five Sections.
Are we, and the Diſſenters all <hi>Blaſphemers</hi> for leaving this
Diviſion out of our Tranſlation? If it be anſwer'd, that
ſome <hi>Heb.</hi> Copies have not theſe Five Sections or Books of
the Pſalter (which I know not, nor will trouble my ſelf to
examin) I ask which are the true and uncorrupted Copies?
(for both cannot be) and why do we follow the latter Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies
rather than thoſe which are <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in all Men's hands?
The Books of the Prophets are thus, intitul'd, <hi>The Book of
the Prophet Iſaiah,</hi> &amp;c. and the Apoſtles Epiſtles thus, <hi>The
Epiſtle of Paul to the Romans,</hi> &amp;c. I cannot think the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd
Prophets and Apoſtles ſet theſe <hi>Titles</hi> on the head of
their Books or Letters. For they prefixt their Names them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
at the beginning and as part of the Body of thoſe
Books and Letters, but the <hi>Titles</hi> on the top were added
for conveniency. There needed no Inſpiration to do this.
The general <hi>Title</hi> of <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Books of the New Teſtament
is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but is not Canonical, ſay <hi>Grotius</hi> and
<hi>Hammond</hi> (and yet they Comment upon it) being added
by the Church, when the Inſpir'd Books were put together.
That <hi>Title, The Epiſtle of Paul the Apoſtle to the Hebrews,</hi> is
found in all MSS. Copies (ſays <hi>Beza)</hi> except one only,
which I hope will break no ſquares. Now <hi>Grotius</hi> is of
Opinion <hi>Luke</hi> wrote this Epiſtle, others <hi>Barnabas,</hi> ſome
<hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> that the Author is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
this being the very Reaſon many Churches receiv'd
not this Epiſtle into the Canon of a good while. I muſt not
paſs the particular Reaſon which the <hi>Latin</hi> Churches gave
for their rejecting this Epiſtle to the <hi>Heb. ſc.</hi> becauſe <hi>ſome
things were in it favouring the Novatian Hereſie,</hi> as they then
judg'd. Mr. <hi>Pool</hi> imputes this to their <hi>Ignorance,</hi> but chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges
them not with <hi>Blaſphemy:</hi> nor did I ever hear that
<hi>Grotius, Hammond,</hi> and the reſt who deny <hi>Paul</hi> to be the
Author of this Epiſtle, were ever cenſur'd as <hi>Blaſphemers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>John</hi> doubtleſs was the Author of thoſe three Epiſtles
that go under his Name, but not of the <hi>Titles</hi> alſo. This
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39246:3"/>
Apoſtle and Evangeliſt for ſome ſpecial Reaſons conceal'd
his Name, when he wrote contrary to the practice of the
reſt. Nor can I believe any other inſpir'd Perſon affixt
thoſe <hi>Titles,</hi> it being highly improbable, that <hi>John</hi> by the
Spirit ſhould conceal himſelf, and another by the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
ſhould diſcover him. I hope Mr. <hi>O.</hi> will not call me <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer</hi>
for this. The meaning of all is, the Church of God
did ever take the Liberty of giving <hi>Titles</hi> unto Books ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines
by Conjecture, and ſometimes of certain knowledge,
as we at this day prefix the Contents before Chapters, and
call the Books of Pſalms in Metre, <hi>The Pſalms of David,</hi>
which is not the <hi>Hebrew Title,</hi> Or elſe the Copiers of them
did it for obvious Reaſons. <hi>viz.</hi> that holy Men might more
readily upon occaſion go to ſuch Books, and conſult 'em,
as they lay in their Cloſets or Libraries among other Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes
of the Scripture. Briefly the <hi>Titles</hi> of the Pſalms and
of the ſeveral Books of Scripture muſt (as I conceive) run
the ſame fate; all muſt be of a certainty Canonical or none
at all can be.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has himſelf confeſt enough to overthrow the
whole Fabrick of his elaborate Diſcourſe on this Subject.
He acknowledges,<note place="margin">Vind. p. 47.</note> 
               <hi>It was a prevailing Opinion, that all the
Pſalms were Penn'd by</hi> David, <hi>that</hi> Auguſt, Chryſoſt. <hi>and</hi> Bede,
<hi>and ſeveral Jewiſh Doctors thought ſo.</hi> What then will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
of the <hi>Title</hi> of the <hi>90th.</hi> and of many other Pſalms?
Were they of a certainty of their Penning, unto whom they
are aſcrib'd in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text? Or is the Rector <hi>ſingular
in a doubtful Point,</hi> when he has ſo many giving in their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
on his ſide? Tho' by the way I ſee no great harm in
being <hi>ſingular,</hi> when the Point is <hi>doubtful,</hi> but much more
I apprehend not that there is any <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> in ſuch <hi>Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity.</hi>
Beſides I pray Sir take notice, how Mr. <hi>O.</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
himſelf concerning the <hi>Title</hi> of the 137. Pſal. <hi>It is
not material to us, who compos'd it, we are ſatisfied it was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely
inspir'd.</hi> But is it not as material that one <hi>Pſalm</hi>
ſhould have a <hi>Title</hi> to unſold its Myſteries as another? And
why will not he give me leave to declare my ſelf thus? <hi>It is
not material to me what becomes of the</hi> Titles, <hi>I am ſatisfy'd
the Pſalms themſelves were d<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vinely Inſpir'd. I make no recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of thoſe Critical Diſputes about the 90th. Pſal. whether</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:39246:4"/>
Moſes, <hi>or</hi> David, <hi>or any other Inſpir'd Perſon penn'd that
Pſalm, I am content to believe it Canonical.</hi> Great then is
the power of Truth you ſee: It will out ſometimes even
before a Man is aware.</p>
            <p>But after all this, I will now ſuppoſe (what I believe you
will not grant) that Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has clear'd his Point beyond
contradiction, yet ſtill I muſt condemn Mr. <hi>D.</hi> (and his
Vindicator too) for reflecting on <hi>us,</hi> becauſe we leave out
an eſſential part of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> in our Liturgy Tranſlation.
I argu'd formerly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ser.</hi> p. 4. <hi>R. R.</hi> p. 15.</note> 
               <hi>The Diſſenters tranſlate 'em not all;</hi> 
               <q>ſome
part of 'em Tranſlated is thruſt out of the Text into the
Margin, like a various Reading, or mere conjecture, or
as not material;</q> but to this he offers nothing. I added,
<hi>They leave 'em out of the Metrical Pſalms, neither do they ſing
'em.</hi> But he endeavours to take off this Retort thus, <hi>The</hi>
Titles <hi>were not deſign'd to be ſung.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> p. 53.</note> Good! 'Tis my very Plea
in Defence of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> our Liturgy Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation
was deſign'd for ſinging, but the <hi>Titles</hi> were not.
No, ſays Mr. <hi>O. You read that Tranſlation.</hi> I anſwer, 1. Some
negligent Miniſters do indeed read 'em; 'tis their Fault,
2. Some conforming Nonconformiſts will read 'em; 'tis
their Crime, 3. Some cannot prevail with their People to
bear a part in the rehearſing 'em; 'tis their Unhappineſs.
But ſtill this Tranſlation is deſign'd not for Reading and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
in the Publick Worſhip, but Devotion. For the
Order of the Church is that the <hi>Pſalms</hi> in this Tranſlation
ſhould be <hi>ſaid or ſung;</hi> ſaid? that is at leaſt repeated <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatim,</hi>
by Miniſter and People, which is a ſpecies of
ſinging, as we believe. Obſerve then, they are ſung in all
Cathedrals, they are repeated in multitudes of Parochial
Churches, and Noblemens Chappels. What would the
Man have more? Shall the Infelicity of ſome Miniſters, the
Treachery of others, or the Careleſsneſs of another ſort be
thought ſufficient to force the Church to take new mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
and lay aſide her Liturgy Tranſlation? I trow not.
Beſides you ſhould obſerve further, that if the <hi>Titles</hi> be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical,
they ought at leaſt to have been <hi>Printed</hi> with the
Metrical <hi>Pſalms,</hi> tho' not ſung: So the Jews did. Briefly
here's nothing but Cavil, not a ſhadow of Anſwer. But
Mr. <hi>O.</hi> concludes, <hi>Their</hi> (the Diſſenters) <hi>not reading the</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:39246:4"/>
Titles (in the Congregation and out of the other Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)
<hi>is an Innocent Omiſſion.</hi> Hem! an Innocent Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?
Verily I cannot get this down. If the <hi>Titles</hi> be an
Eſſential part of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and uſeful to unfold the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
in them, as Mr. <hi>O.</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>D.</hi> will have it, can there
be a more Sacrilegious Omiſſion than firſt not to Tranſlate
the <hi>Titles</hi> exactly, and then neglect the Reading them?
Not to make uſe of the Canonical Key, but to burſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently
and blindly into the Chambers of Divine Secrets,
like Thieves and Robbers? Beſides a little Juſtice would
have taught Mr. <hi>O.</hi> that our <hi>not Printing</hi> the <hi>Titles</hi> is as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent
an Omiſſion, as their <hi>not Reading</hi> 'em. One might
reaſonably expect juſt Weights and Meaſures. Either let
the whole body of Chriſtians throughout the World come
under the Charge of being Corrupters of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> or
let the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Rector paſs in the Croud
as Innocent alſo. Why ſhould we be made an Example,
when even our Accuſers themſelves are guilty of the ſame
Omiſſion? I leave you then to judge how well Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has
acquitted himſelf on this firſt Queſtion.</p>
            <p>The next is about the Verſes interpolated <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
you to what I have in Sermon and <hi>R. R.</hi> offer'd on this
Argument, and to inform your ſelf thence whether Mr. <hi>D.</hi>
did honeſtly impute it unto <hi>us,</hi> that <hi>we</hi> foiſted them in, and
whether Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has thoroughly juſtify'd him. But I'll in a
few words conſider Mr. <hi>O.</hi>'s Vindication of <hi>Jerom,</hi> whom
he would ſain lick clean, if it were poſſible. He informs us,
who they are that have commended him, and it's confeſt
he was a great Man, but perhaps his trueſt Character is,
<hi>Magnae virtutes, nec minora</hi>—In the Point about Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
it has been often enough laid to his charge, that he
ſays and unſays, and contradicts himſelf. In the Letters
which he exchang'd with St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> he maintain'd the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs
of Diſſimulation, and endeavour'd to excuſe <hi>Peter</hi>
and <hi>Barnabas.</hi> He is believed to have been diſguſted for nor
being made a Biſhop, and on that ſcore depreſſed the Order
as low as he could with any colour of Truth. Nor did he
eſcape the ſuſpicion of—Beſides, he was ſo
bent againſt the <hi>LXX.</hi> that he bluſht not to abuſe 'em,
chuſing to repreſent 'em by ſome corrupt Copies, rather
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39246:5"/>
than by the known and unqueſtionable reading. I will give
you two Inſtances. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. 10. cited by St. John 19. 37.
<hi>They ſhall look on him whom they pierced,</hi> Jerom's <hi>LXX</hi> it
ſeems read not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even as our <hi>LXX</hi>
doth at this day. But <hi>Jerom</hi> might (if he would have been
ingenuous) have taken notice of what he could not be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,
that the right reading in the <hi>LXX</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
as is witneſſed by four Fathers more early than himſelf.
<hi>Juſtin M.</hi> in his Dialogue againſt <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew. <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi>
likewiſe frequently.<note place="margin">De Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect. c. 26, 51. De car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Chriſti c. 24.</note> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his 20 Teſtimony
againſt thoſe People. To whom add <hi>Lactantius</hi> alſo, <hi>Zach.
13.</hi> 4. He makes the <hi>LXX</hi> ſpeak perfect Nonſenſe, <hi>non
ſum Prophetes ego, quia Homo genuit me à Juventute meâ.</hi>
Whereas even in our preſent <hi>LXX</hi> we read thus agreeably
with the <hi>Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
Finally
I obſerv'd in <hi>R. R.</hi> how ſcandalouſly he abus'd St. <hi>Luke.</hi> No,
replies Mr. <hi>O.</hi> For as <hi>Paul</hi> is call'd a <hi>Babler</hi> by the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
ſo was <hi>Luke</hi> accounted by the Nations an <hi>obſcure vile
Perſon and of no great credit,</hi> not by <hi>Jerom,</hi> tho' <hi>Jerom</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates
it, as <hi>Luke</hi> did that of <hi>Paul.</hi> But there are many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
between the one and the other. <hi>Luke</hi> was an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd
Hiſtorian, flouriſh'd when what he relates of <hi>Paul</hi>
happen'd, it may be had his Relation from the Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
and had no Cauſe to ſupport: But <hi>Jerom</hi> liv'd about
350 Years after <hi>Luke,</hi> Writes what he backs with no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
or probable proof, and was now calling into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
the truth of <hi>Luke</hi>'s Hiſtory. There is then all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
in the World to believe that this Character of <hi>Luke,</hi> tho'
father'd on the Gentiles, was the Iſſue of <hi>Jerom</hi>'s own Brain,
to diſparage the <hi>LXX</hi> and to ſet up the <hi>Heb.</hi> Bible. Nor
did St. <hi>Luke write the Acts for the uſe of the Gentiles,</hi> as Mr.
<hi>O.</hi> aſſerts, tho' in time ('tis true) it might fall into their
hands. But the Hiſtorian addreſſes it to <hi>Theophilus</hi> a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
Chap. 1. 1. And what if <hi>Jerom</hi>'s <hi>Gentes</hi> were the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile
Believers? Did they eſteem <hi>Luke</hi> obſcure, vile and of
little Reputation? Sure (if this was his meaning) <hi>Jerom</hi>
was not a little miſtaken, to ſpeak as ſoftly as I can. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
can any one believe <hi>Luke</hi> was leſs conſiderable among
the unbelieving Nations, than the other Inſpir'd Writers?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39246:5"/>
He was the moſt learned of 'em all, except perhaps <hi>Paul.</hi>
His Greek (as Criticks ſay) is the pureſt of all. He was a
known Phyſician, which doubtleſs commended him to the
eſteem of the Nations, both Jews and Gentiles as he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd
along with <hi>Paul,</hi> and that <hi>before his Writings were ever
publiſhed.</hi> So that <hi>Jerom</hi> cannot be ſhelter'd by pretending,
not he, but the Nations accounted him <hi>obſcure,</hi> &amp;c. For
this Father further affirms, <hi>Non debuit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>St. Luke ought
not to write any thing contrary to the Scriptures, that were then
in the hands of the Nations,</hi> that is contrary to the corrupt
<hi>LXX.</hi> Here you ſee, he magiſterially declares what the
Spirit of God ought not to do. Belike for fear of diſobli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
them, who as yet had not the <hi>Hebrew</hi> verity among
them. Right <hi>Jerom</hi> all over. The Inſpir<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Evangeliſt <hi>Luke</hi>
to ſerve a ſmall turn muſt tell a Lye: Or leſt he ſhould
offend the Nations, muſt diſſemble the Truth, <hi>The Hebrew
verity,</hi> and this without all regard to the Jews, and Jewiſh
Converts, whom he muſt needs ſcandalize thereby. Here
is Diſſimulation with a witneſs, and made a neceſſary Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<hi>(non debuit)</hi> in an Inſpir'd Pen-man of Scripture. Whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
is diſpos'd to vindicate <hi>Jerom,</hi> may go to his Letters
written to St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> and furniſh himſelf with Arguments
enow to that purpoſe. But ſhall a Man lye for God? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<hi>Jerom</hi>'s much Oriental Learning made him mad, I will
not ſay <hi>a Blaſphemer.</hi> In fine, that <hi>Jerom</hi> fram'd this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
for <hi>Luke</hi> in the name of the Nations will appear from
what he adds. Hoc generaliter obſervandum, quòd ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque
SS. Apoſtoli &amp; Apoſtolici viri loquuntur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,
iis plerumque Teſtimoniis abutuntur, quae jam fuerant
in Gentibus divulgata. <hi>The Holy Apoſtles and Apoſtolick
Men</hi> (neglecting the Hebrew verity) <hi>when they ſpeak to the
People, make uſe of thoſe Teſtimonies,</hi> (viz. which <hi>Jerom</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
were miſtaken and falſe) <hi>out of the LXX. which had
already been divulg'd among the Nations</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Is not this
<hi>ſuperfine</hi> Doctrine? One needs not be <hi>Hypercritical</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
hence, that <hi>Jerom</hi> makes the Apoſtles and their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions
in Preaching the Goſpel to be a Pack of Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers,
and guilty of the ſame pious Frauds and holy Cheats,
that he before ſuggeſted particularly of <hi>Luke.</hi> Once more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39246:6"/>
Commenting on <hi>Mic.</hi> 5. 2. He thus delivers himſelf, Sunt
autem qui aſſerunt, &amp;c. <hi>There are who affirm</hi> (I believe
no body but himſelf) <hi>that almoſt in all the Teſtimonies which
are brought out of the Old Teſtament this Error is committed,
either that the Order is chang'd, or the Words, and ſometimes
the very ſenſe is different, the Apoſtles or Evangeliſts not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering
their Teſtimonies out of the Book, but truſting to their
Memories, which ſometimes faild them.</hi> Sir, Can you read
theſe Lines without Horrour and Amaſement? The Spirit
of God ſurely (whereby they wrote) forgot not himſelf,
tho' they did. That which follows from the whole is, that
<hi>Jerom</hi> is not defended. The <hi>LXX.</hi> as to that Paſſage in
the <hi>Acts</hi> Chap. 7. was in <hi>Jerom</hi>'s days more correct, than
the <hi>Hebrew</hi> verity now is, and that the <hi>LXX.</hi> was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd
by the Inſpir'd Infallible Apoſtles, and Apoſtolical
Men, as <hi>Jerom</hi> acknowledgeth. May it not then be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd
hence as probable, that <hi>Paul</hi> follow'd them in his
<hi>3d.</hi> to the <hi>Romans</hi> v. 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and tranſcrib'd the Verſes
out of the then <hi>LXX?</hi> O! but the Greek Fathers do not
Comment on theſe Verſes. Suppoſing this (for I have
'em not ready at hand, nor leiſure to examin them all)
the Reaſon may be, either they Commented on them in
other places, or it was an <hi>innocent Omiſſion,</hi> or elſe 'tis
but a negative Argument and unconcluding. But after
all, let us imagine the Three Verſes have been interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated,
this is no juſt Excuſe of Mr. <hi>D.</hi> who accus'd <hi>us</hi>
for foiſting them in. Why may not we do ſo as well as,
and after <hi>Paul?</hi> And beſides they are in the Latin Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
Verſion, which was in uſe in <hi>Jerom</hi>'s days, and is ſtill
in good Credit with Mr. <hi>O.</hi> You may ſee more Reaſons
given to excuſe the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Serm. p. 7. <hi>R. R.</hi>
p. 18. which I will not trouble you with. Here I leave
this part of the Controverſie to the Judgment of any Man
of Underſtanding, whether Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has vindicated either
<hi>Jerom</hi> or Mr. <hi>D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queſtion about the Three Verſes <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd
a more general one concerning the <hi>LXX.</hi> and the
<hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies of the Old Teſtament: The former are by
my Adverſaries ſaid to have been corrupted; and I gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39246:6"/>
it, but withal affirm'd that ſo are the <hi>Hebrew</hi> alſo.
But Mr. <hi>O.</hi> undertakes to prove they were not corrupted
before and in our Saviour's days.</p>
            <p>Here I muſt premiſe (becauſe Mr. <hi>O.</hi> makes ſuch an hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous
Out-cry againſt the Rector, as if he were about de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving
the Church of the Scriptures, and a Divine Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of the reveal'd Will of God) that my Argument is
not intended, neither looks that way at all, as any fair Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary
would grant. The Truths of Revelation are to be
ſought for, not out of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text <hi>only,</hi> nor out of the
<hi>LXX. only,</hi> but out of both, which lend their helping hand
to one another, together with all other Ancient Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
and thoſe numerous Quotations of Scripture which
we meet with in the Fathers. And I humbly conceive no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
miniſters more advantage unto Atheiſts, than obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately
to contend that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text is not in the leaſt
corrupted, and to ſtrip us of all other means of correcting
it. Now Mr. <hi>O.</hi> attempts to evince his Opinion by Three
Arguments.</p>
            <p>I. That the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Bibles are <hi>de facto</hi> incorrupt.</p>
            <p>II. That the Jews could not.</p>
            <p>III. Would not corrupt them. The firſt he confirms
thus, <hi>Becauſe Chriſt never charg'd the Jews with corrupting
them. A.</hi> If the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text was the ſame in Chriſt's as
in our days (which Mr. <hi>O.</hi> muſt acknowledg) then it had
been corrupted in Chriſt's time: This appears afterwards.
Beſides I retort his Reaſon thus, the <hi>LXX.</hi> was not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
in the Apoſtles days, becauſe they never charg'd
that Verſion with any Corruptions, as they would and
ought to have done. As Chriſt bids his Diſciples <hi>to ſearch
the Scriptures</hi> (the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copy) So St. <hi>Paul</hi> commends
the <hi>Bereans</hi> that they <hi>ſearched the Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi>
that by his Mother and Grandmother he had been train'd
up in the Knowledge of the Scriptures, <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>LXX.</hi> for
all theſe were either Gentiles, or Gentile Proſelytes, or
Helleniſtical Jews, and therefore us'd the <hi>LXX.</hi> When <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi>
and <hi>Jerom</hi> ſpeak thus, <hi>That moſt of the allegations made
by Chriſt and his Apoſtles out of the Old Teſtament are ſtill
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39246:7"/>
there,</hi> they plainly enough confeſs that <hi>ſome</hi> are not, and
conſequently there muſt have been a corruption of the Old
Scriptures according to theſe Fathers. On the other hand
I<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll give you a better Argument in proof of their Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they had been corrupted before <hi>Ezra</hi>'s
time, <hi>who</hi> (ſay moſt of the Fathers) <hi>corrected the Errors
that had crept in afore-time, and amended them, as the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews
report.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Synop. in Ez. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Now tell me, is it not much more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
that they were ſomewhat corrupted between <hi>Ezra</hi> and
Chriſt? Had God a greater care of the Scriptures under
the ſecond Temple, than under the firſt, when Prophets
were common among them? But of this more by and by.</p>
            <p>2. Mr. <hi>O.</hi> in his Harangue here inſinuates that I affirm
<hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Corruption of the Hebrew Copies,</hi> but 'tis Mr. <hi>O</hi>'s
own fancy not mine; and beſides he talks very highly of
Providence, even as if there lay an abſolute engagement
on God, either not to ſuffer any Corruption, or miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly
to diſcover it. <hi>A</hi> Why then has Providence per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
ſo many various Readings in the New Teſtament?
and why has not God by ſome extraordinary means told
us, whether the latter Period <hi>1 Jo.</hi> 2. 23. was written by
Divine Inſpiration, or added by ſome Tranſcriber? The
ſumm is, Providence has taken care that all the material
neceſſary and Eſſential Doctrines of Religion are ſtill abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
preſerved in the Scriptures, and no falſe Doctrines
therein eſtabliſh'd, which I take to be true both of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi>
the <hi>LXX.</hi> and the New Teſtament. But ſtill in all
Ages before Printing, Corruptions of other kinds crept in,
and God for Reaſons beſt known to his Wiſdom has permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
it.</p>
            <p>3. It muſt be granted a pious Jew would not purpoſely
Corrupt the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text, but others would. That very
Talmudical Tale<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that one <hi>Solomon</hi> endeavour'd to root <hi>Jod</hi>
out of the Text ſhews that ſome Jews would have Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text. You ſee how unconcluding Mr. <hi>O</hi>'s.
Arguments are. In a word, that the Jews would have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
the Word of God in the Propheſies pointing at Jeſus
Chriſt, is undeniably true from <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> his Dialogue,
wherein he chargeth them with it. It muſt be allow'd
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39246:7"/>
thence that they had inclination enough to attempt it, or
elſe the Martyr could in no wiſe be excuſed; whether
they were ſucceſsful is to be examin'd in the next place,
and</p>
            <p>1. From the Teſtimony of <hi>Juſtin</hi> and in anſwer to Mr. <hi>O.</hi>
I affirm,</p>
            <p>1. That <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> did underſtand both the <hi>Hebrew</hi>
and <hi>Syriac</hi> Languages, and ſo doubtleſs was acquainted
with the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Bible. For in Apology <hi>2d.</hi> He calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<hi>the Son of</hi> Priſcus Bacchius <hi>born or come from</hi> Flavia Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apolis
<hi>in the Syrian Paleſtine.</hi> Accordingly I find him play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Critic upon the Etymology of <hi>Satanas,</hi> Dialog. p. 331.
deriving it from the Jewiſh and Syrian Tongue; <hi>Sata,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying
<hi>Apoſtata, &amp; Nas, Serpens.</hi> Yea, Mr. <hi>O</hi>'s. inſtance
proves him skill'd in the <hi>Hebrew;</hi> nor was he miſtaken
when he affirm'd, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> imported <hi>homo vincens virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies Virtue, Fortitude, one of the great At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes
of God, which Mr. <hi>O</hi>'s Novice did not conſider.
And God oft in Scripture makes an Attribute to be as it
were his proper Name, <hi>1 Sam. 15. 29. The ſtrength of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael
<hi>cannot lye,</hi> that is, God cannot. So <hi>Jacob as a Prince
had power with</hi> Fortitude it ſelf, that is, with <hi>God.</hi> And that
<hi>Juſtin</hi> by <hi>Virtue</hi> meant no other than God, may be ſeen
Dial. p. 285. where he ſo reads the place, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>2. It is not then the <hi>LXX.</hi> only us'd in the Synagogues,
that <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> challengeth as corrupted by the Jews,
but the <hi>Hebrew</hi> alſo. For after he had defended the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of the <hi>LXX.</hi> then among the Chriſtians, to have been
exactly true in the places before ſpoken of, and had chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leng'd
the Jews (p. 297.) for having eras'd out of theirs
many intire Paſſages, which foretold the Crucifixion of
Jeſus Chriſt God and Man, which places becauſe the Jews
deny'd to belong unto the Scripture, <hi>Juſtin</hi> promiſes to
make good his general Charge out of thoſe very Scriptures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
which the Jews acknowledg'd to be genuine, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly
produces a Paſſage out of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> two out of <hi>Iſaiah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
and that of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96. 10, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which Obſervations
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39246:8"/>
he had made out of the Scriptures, which the Jews read
in their Synagogues (p. 298.) And he adds, theſe Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
or at leaſt one had crept in very lately. To all
which <hi>Trypho</hi> had not a word to ſay. It hence appears that
<hi>Juſtin</hi> argues not out of his own ſingle Copies of the <hi>LXX.</hi>
which Mr. <hi>O.</hi> ſeems to grant had theſe Paſſages, but out of
many Copies us'd in the Jewiſh Synagogues, which the
Father had carefuly examin'd, and in all likelihood <hi>Hebrew</hi>
Copies too in Paleſtine of <hi>Syria,</hi> whereof he was a Native.
Nor can we ſuppoſe <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> argu'd from his own
<hi>Greek</hi> Copy only, but thoſe commonly in the hands of the
Chriſtians. He had more ſenſe than ſo to impoſe upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
and <hi>Trypho</hi> too.</p>
            <p>3. It muſt be confeſſed it is a wonder that even after <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>
had thus noted theſe Corruptions, the Chriſtians ſhould
not have amended them. But I can produce Mr. <hi>O.</hi> a like
Inſtance, which muſt be acknowledg'd parallel. All the
<hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies that we have (as far as I can learn) and
mine in particular has that of <hi>Pſal. 22. 16. As a Lion,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
of <hi>They pierced;</hi> and I have conſulted <hi>Pagnine,</hi> who
renders it <hi>tanquam Leo,</hi> though in the Margin he has <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt.</hi>
And though all agree that <hi>they pierced</hi> is the true
Reading, and though ſome ſeem to have found a few Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies
in <hi>Hebrew</hi> which have it ſo, yet for the two Ages laſt
paſt, wherein Learning has ſuperabounded they have not
corrected this <hi>Erratum.</hi> Our beloved Jews doubtleſs will
not ſuffer us; and we haply are as unwilling as they, leſt
the Infallibility of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text to a title, like that of
the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, ſhould come to nothing, for this Change
would be an open acknowledgment of its Corruption. Let
then Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> call me <hi>Foulmouth,</hi> and Mr. <hi>O. Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi>
I am ſtill of Opinion, and do aver upon the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of <hi>J. M.</hi> that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies the Jewiſh <hi>LXX.</hi>
and both have receiv'd ſome Corruptions. But to return,
If the places had been found in any of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies
in the days of <hi>Juſtin,</hi> it had been an eaſie matter for <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ph<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
and the Jews to have appeal'd to the Original <hi>Hebrew</hi>
Verity for their Juſtification, and retorted upon <hi>J. Martyr,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:39246:8"/>
that the Chriſtians rather had been the Authors of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd
Interpolations, for the ſupport and advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of their Religion. They might the more confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
have done this, if <hi>J. M.</hi> had not underſtood the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Chronological Argument I will not meddle with;
I muſt either Tranſcribe <hi>Voſſius,</hi> or waſt more Time and
Paper than is needful, ſince any one may have the intire
Argument at the Fountain Head; but to treat of it in
ſhort, as Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has done, and over-look the moſt, and
the beſt of the Arguments, would be to ſmall purpoſe. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
remember that <hi>Voſſius</hi> eſtabliſhes the Chronology of the
<hi>LXX.</hi> by the Teſtimony of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> between whom there
is a very near Agreement: And all the World knows that
<hi>Joſephus</hi> was a learned Man, a ſaithful Hiſtorian, a Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh
Prieſt and Interpreter of the Law, and therefore could
not be very much miſtaken in this matter. But whereas
Mr. <hi>O.</hi> ſuggeſts p. 70. that upon this Principle of 6000
Years we cannot prove Chriſt is yet come, I reply 1. It
may upon that very Principle be prov'd, if we will admit
(as we ought) the <hi>LXX.</hi> into our aſſiſtance. 2. Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Chronology right, it is not neceſſary for
us to follow the Jewiſh Principle of 6000 Years; it's ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
to ſay, (let what will become of the Chronology
whether it be 4 or 6000 Years) that the time of Chriſt's
Appearance in the Fleſh was come in the days of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus
Ceſar,</hi> when both Jews and Samaritans were big with
expectations of him, and thereby acknowledg'd the time
to be fulfill'd. Which time, if they believ'd to be 6000
Years it is not unlikely, but they corrupted the <hi>Hebrew</hi>
Chronology, to juſtifie their not Believing and Crucifying
Him.</p>
            <p>The Inſtance of <hi>Cainan, Luke</hi> 3. in Chriſt's Genealogy,
left out of the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> is ſo clear, that one might juſtly
admire good Authors ſhould ſo toil and ſweat, to avoid
<hi>Luke</hi>'s Teſtimony, and all for the ſake of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.
I can give a plauſible Reaſon, why the Jews might
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39246:9"/>
leave <hi>Cainan</hi> out of the <hi>Heb. viz.</hi> Becauſe thereby they
would diſparage and overthrow <hi>Luke</hi>'s Genealogy, and ſpoil
his credit among the Nations. As for other Additions unto
the <hi>LXX.</hi> 'tis nothing to the Point. It is confeſs'd the <hi>LXX.</hi>
has been corrupted: But 'tis—(I will not ſay <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy)</hi>
to impute Corruption unto that place, which has
receiv'd Teſtimony from the Spirit of God by the Pen of
<hi>Luke.</hi> But ſays Dr. <hi>Lightfoot, Luke muſt follow the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then's
Bibles in his Quotations.</hi> That is, <hi>Luke</hi> an Inſpir'd
Penman <hi>(debet,</hi> as <hi>Jerom</hi> before him) muſt leave the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi>
Verity, and tranſcribe out of a corrupt Verſion of
the Scriptures. Some haply would think this not far off
<hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> but I will not reflect ſo ſeverely on that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
and learned Gentleman. 2. The Doctor, adds, <hi>Luke
was but a Copyer and not a Corrector</hi> But he was an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd
Copyer, and ought by the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Verity to have
amended, at leaſt not have follow'd the Corrupt <hi>LXX.</hi>
Ay but, <hi>the Gentiles well acquainted with the</hi> LXX <hi>would
then have call'd</hi> Luke<hi>'s veracity into Queſtion.</hi> A. So they
did, if <hi>Jerom</hi> is to be believ'd; however, <hi>Luke</hi> ought not,
doubtleſs did not value this. Let God be true, but
every Man a Lyar. Shall an Inſpir'd Writer value his own
veracity above the Truth of God's Word? The Dr. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes,
<hi>Luke in the reſt was a Faithful Tranſcriber.</hi> Very
good, I think ſo. And why not in this? Or how can a
Man believe <hi>him</hi> in any thing, who was unfaithful in one,
or two? Here is a curious Principle, upon which <hi>Jerom</hi>'s
lawfulneſs of Diſſimulation, and the Papiſts <hi>pia fraudes,</hi>
and officious Lies may be vindicated, and differs very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
from that Maxim of <hi>Jerom, Quod ubicunque SS. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli
&amp; Apoſtolici viri loquuntur ad populos, iis plerumque
teſtimoniis abutuntur, quae jam fuerant in Gentibus divulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</hi>
The Apoſtles it ſeems were very cautious of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
the Gentiles, but not of ſcandalizing the Jews, and
the Jewiſh Proſelytes, by this unfaithful repreſentation of
the Hiſtory of the Jewiſh Church and Chriſt's Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39246:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
To the Corruption, noted, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 22. 16. Mr. <hi>O.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies,
and mentions ſeveral <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies, which read,
<hi>they pierced.</hi> Very well, and is not this a fair Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies have in this place gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
been corrupted? And I ask, how ſhall the true
Reading be adjuſted, but by the Teſtimony of the LXX?
For the Paſſage is not once cited in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<hi>It is no wonder</hi> (Mr. <hi>O.</hi> ſays) <hi>the Jews ſhould
prefer that Reading which favours their Cauſe.</hi> Right,
but 'tis wonder upon wonder to me, the Chriſtian
Sticklers for the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Verity, ſhould continue it ſtill
in the Text, for fear, (I ſuppoſe) of offending the
<hi>Jews,</hi> without any regard to the Chriſtians, and to the
Truth. Or, rather as Mr. <hi>O</hi>'s. Story of the <hi>Famous
Dan. Bomb.</hi> for fear of loſing the Sale of their Bibles ſo
corrected; for which Reaſon he might better be ſtyl'd
<hi>Infamous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I add again that Paſſage,</hi> Deut. 32. 8. According to
the number of the Angels, <hi>even</hi> Jerom <hi>himſelf thus reads
it.</hi> Quatuor ventos coeli; quatuor arbitror Angelicas po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtates,
quibus principalia Regna commiſſa ſunt, juxta il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud
quod in <hi>Deuter,</hi> legimus, Quando dividebat altiſſimus,
Gentes, quando ſeparabat filios <hi>Adam,</hi> conſtituit Terminos po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulorum,
juxta numerum Angelorum Dei. <hi>It muſt then
be confeſſed, that this was the true Reading in</hi> Jerom<hi>'s
time, but not ſo now. The</hi> Hebrew <hi>Copies therefore at
this day are here corrupted, if</hi> Jerom <hi>may be credited.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more, take notice, that there is, at this day, a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text, in the <hi>1 Sam.</hi> 2. 17. Where
it plainly diſcovers it ſelf, the Courſe of the Story be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
intolerably perplext and tranſpos'd, as any one will
diſcern, reading the latter end of the <hi>16th,</hi> the whole
<hi>17th,</hi> and beginning of the <hi>18th</hi> Chapter. But I will
not enlarge on this, nor trouble you with thoſe lame
Solutions of this Difficulty, which I meet with in the
<hi>Synopſis;</hi> all of 'em devis'd to ſalve up the Credit and
Infallibility of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Verity; whereas the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedite
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39246:10"/>
and Satisfactory Way, if Men could lay aſide
Prejudices, is to correct the place by the LXX.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> bleſſing the ſeveral Tribes of <hi>Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 33. 6.
Thus ſpeaks of <hi>Reuben</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew: Let Reuben live
and not die, and let his men, (his poſterity) be few.</hi> For
tho' our Tranſlators have helped the place by adding
the Negative (which indeed ought to be there, elſe
<hi>Moſes</hi> Curſes that Tribe, inſtead of Bleſſing it) yet it is
not in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> as is acknowledg'd by our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators,
putting the Negative <hi>not,</hi> in a different Character.
Here, again, the Criticks in the <hi>Synopſis</hi> take a
deal of Pains to patch up the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Verity, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any Satisfaction to me, I do profeſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But let us now take a view of</hi> Jerom, <hi>who will appear
not ſo tight and ſo firmly perſwaded of the Incorruption
of the</hi> Hebrew <hi>Text, as Mr.</hi> O. <hi>is, Commenting on that
Paſſage,</hi> Gal. 3. 13. Curſed is every one that hangeth on
a tree. <hi>He delivers himſelf thus,</hi> Ex quo mihi videtur,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> From whence it ſeems to me, either that the ancient
<hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies read the words otherwiſe, than at preſent,
or the Apoſtle expreſſed the Senſe of the Scriptures, not the
Words, or (which is rather to be thought) that the Name
of God was after the Paſſion of Chriſt, by ſome body ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
to the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and to our Bibles, that he might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage
us, who bolieve in Chriſt <hi>(as if)</hi> accurſed of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again, on</hi> Micah 5. 2. <hi>He obſerves that many Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
or Villages, eleven in number, are reckon'd up,</hi>
(Joſ. 15. 60.) <hi>in the LXX, tho' not in the</hi> Hebrew, <hi>and
amongſt the reſt,</hi> Ephratah, <hi>or</hi> Bethlehem, <hi>which belong'd
to the Tribe of</hi> Judah, <hi>whence Chriſt ſprang,</hi> Matth. 2.
6. <hi>He then adds,</hi> ſive d<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> veterihus eraſum ſit militia
Judeorum. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We know not certainly, whether it was
ſtruck out of the Ancient Copies thro' the Malice of the
<hi>Jews,</hi> leaſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould hence appear to have ſprang from
the. Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> or whether it was added by the LXX.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39246:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>But enough, and more (I hope) than needed on this
Point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having, I ſuppoſe, made good my Aſſertion, that the
<hi>Hebrew</hi> Bibles have been corrupted in all Ages<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>; I now
return to the main Buſineſs. When I had been in the
Sermon on the Defenſive, and had vindicated the
Church of <hi>England,</hi> from Mr. <hi>D</hi>'s. frivolous Objections;
and having at that time (it was a time of Peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
us) met with a Pamphlet in great Vogue at
<hi>Mancheſter,</hi> Intituled, <hi>Notes on the B. of</hi> S. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And
another in <hi>M. S.</hi> call'd a Sermon, in both which, we
were vilely, Maliciouſly, and Cauſeleſly traduc'd; and
ſo the Peace being broken, I thought it not improper
to carry the War into the Enemies own Country, and
to let 'em ſee, it was poſſible to give 'em a Diverſion,
Briefly, I taxt them with that Corruption, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. I
argu'd conjecturally, and from Circumſtances, but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
from Matter of Fact. And becauſe Mr. <hi>O.</hi>
was not content with one, and that a <hi>Scotch</hi> Inſtance
too, I then prov'd 'em to have countenanc'd and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
the Corruption by two other Overt Acts, which
render'd my other Conjectures the more probable, and
the main Charge <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt them beyond all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie.
The life of the whole Argument put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
depends on the Evidence of thoſe Matters of Fact,
which, whether Mr. <hi>O.</hi> has vindicated the united Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
from, is now to be conſider'd. But firſt, take
notice, it ought not to ſurprize you, that my Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial
Proofs are made ſo little account of. Even Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors
have Brow enough to ſtand out to the laſt
gaſp againſt ſuch Evidence, and to aſſert their Innocence,
when the Halter is about their Necks, and ſometimes
againſt poſitive Witneſs alſo.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>Cameronian</hi> Inſtance, all that is offer'd of
moment (if that be ſo) is <q>Coll. <hi>Fairfax</hi> heard not the
<hi>Camer.</hi> Urge the corrupt Reading, and that perhaps
the Story paſs'd twenty Hands, before it reach'd
the Collonel.</q> But perhaps it paſſed not above one,
and it is plain the Collonel believ'd it, and we ought
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39246:11"/>
not to think him ſo Eaſie and Credulous, as to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
a Story without good Ground. Beſides, in the
more large Account, I have of the Story, the Reporter
is mention'd by the Collonel, with Honour and Reſpect,
whom he ſtiles a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and <hi>perhaps</hi> inclinable to
the <hi>Cameronian</hi> Faction, yea, <hi>perhaps</hi> that Gentleman
might urge it by way of Diſpute with the Collonel.
What abundance of things may one ſurmiſe? But Mr.
<hi>O.</hi> Pleads, <hi>Perſon, Time and Place, are not nam'd, that
therefore the Evidence is blind, and would look ridiculous
in a Court of Judicature.</hi> The proper Anſwer hereunto,
is, that tho' ſuch Teſtimonies in Courts of Juſtice, are
not accounted ſufficient to ground a Judiciary Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
Sentence upon, yet are they not Ridiculous, but
oft-times believ'd by the Court. An Evidence may be
ſufficient for private Conviction, which will not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd
of, in publick Forms of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> accuſes ſome of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (and he had
it from ſome of the Houſe of <hi>Cloe,</hi> whom he mentions
not, and through how many Hands it paſſed, we know
not) for diſparaging him. <hi>His Letters are weighty and
powerful, but his bodily Preſence is weak and contemptible.</hi>
Here was neither Perſon, nor Time, nor Place nam'd,
and yet <hi>Paul</hi> believ'd the Report. But the Reaſon of
the Collonel's not naming Perſon, Time, and Place, is
obvious. For not thinking any uſe would be made of
the Story, and neglecting to put down theſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
in his Memorials. He eaſily let 'em ſlip out of
his Memory. The Faith of Men is at a low Ebb, if
the want of theſe Circumſtances muſt damn all Reports
as Ridiculous, and eſpecially, when they are but of
yeſterday.</p>
            <p>To the Information of Mr. <hi>Elliſon,</hi> he pleads that
Mr. <hi>Jolly</hi> is dead, and thereby <hi>we are put out of all hopes
of being able to examin the Truth.</hi> I queſtion not, but
you ſee this is meer ſhifting. If Mr. <hi>O.</hi> doth really
ſuſpect the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Veracity of Mr. <hi>Elliſon,</hi> let him (for he has
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39246:11"/>
the means) inquire into ſome of the Circumſtances,
which will in a good meaſure clear the reſt. There
are thoſe in and about <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> who can tell him
there was ſuch a Diſſenting Miniſter as Mr. <hi>Jolly,</hi> that
there is ſuch a Place as <hi>Duckenfield hall,</hi> whether Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters
were wont to reſort, and I doubt not, but it
may be prov'd, that Mr. <hi>E.</hi> and Mr. <hi>J.</hi> were then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd
in ſome Diſputes about Church Diſcipline, and
Government. And if ſo, there is no Reaſon to reject
Mr. <hi>Elliſon</hi>'s Teſtimony, as a meer deviſed Tale. Will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
one ſay this Evidence is a blind one? Would it not
be admitted in a Court of Juſtice? No Judge but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
ſuch Teſtimonies, would decree the Nuncupative
Will of a deceaſed Perſon, Good and Valid.</p>
            <p>As to that Story from the <hi>Bolton</hi> Gentleman, it is an
unexceptionable Proof of what it was produced for.
My Buſineſs was not to ſhew, upon what particular
Point this fals Reading was alledg'd either at <hi>Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenfield,</hi>
or in this Diſpute, whether about Peoples <hi>mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
or <hi>chooſing</hi> their own Miniſters, but that it has been
urg'd <hi>in favour of the Popular Government,</hi> and the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Reading can concern nothing elſe. Nor was the
Queſtion between Mr. <hi>O.</hi> and me, whether any <hi>Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Miniſters,</hi> but any <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters had ever urg'd
the Corrupt Reading,</hi> Rem. <hi>p.</hi> 14. And if theſe Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
Diſputants were ſo ignorant, as they are ſuſpected
to be (for they ſhall be called Ignorant when the
Cauſe requires it, tho' at other times they are the moſt
knowing Perſons) can it with Reaſon be thought, but
that the Argument was put into their Mouths <hi>by ſome
of their Leaders?</hi> Whether Laymen or pretending Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
is of no moment in this Caſe.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole Matter, it is, I hope, manifeſt, that
the Diſſenters, if they did not contrive the <hi>Erratum,</hi>
were juſtly charg'd with owning it, ſeeing they have
endeavour'd to improve it unto their own Advantage.
If they did not beget it, they have at leaſt Father'd it,
and why ſhould we refuſe 'em the Child, which (right,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39246:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or wrong, concerns not us) they lay claim unto, and
no body elſe has a mind to, eſpecially when it was in
requital for ſpiteful and groundleſs Reflections, caſt
on us by the Note-maker without Provocation: For
<hi>requital</hi> ſeems to Mr. <hi>O.</hi> a juſt Reaſon for thus doing.
Now then, if we muſt yet dwell upon that Expoſtulation,
<hi>who began,</hi> and who juſtly <hi>requited?</hi> You will find this
reſolv'd at the entrance of <hi>R. R.</hi> And yet without any
Defence againſt that part of my Apology, we are ſtill
told. <hi>The Note-maker doth not charge any Perſonal Fault of
the Biſhop of</hi> S. <hi>on the whole body of the Epiſcopal Church,</hi>
Vindic. p. 22. But ſee here how Prejudice and Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality
will blind a Man; for he immediately ſubjoyns,
that the Note-maker <hi>retorts the Schiſm upon the Church,</hi>
which the Biſhop of <hi>S.</hi> had ſuppos'd the Diſſenters guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of. Now I think the Epiſcopal Church is here
charg'd with <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuppoſed Fault, that is, taxing
the Diſſenters with Schiſm. He ſhould have let us (at
leaſt of <hi>Mancheſter)</hi> alone; for there the Storm was to
fall, whatever the Title Page ſays it was in <hi>uſum Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
Nor ſhould he have left his Subject, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd
us with Atheiſm, Socinianiſm, Perjury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
What's this to Schiſm? Or was it for the Service of
the Government, to diſcourage Men from. Submitting
to it? I obſerve this, becauſe theſe Men are ſo apt
(like our Dragoons laſt among us) to accuſe every body
of Jacobitiſm, that ſtands in their way, when as none
more effectually promote it than they. And if ſome
ſhall be eſteem'd Perjur'd for the Alteration of their
former Principles, what ſhall we think of a multitude
of Diſſenters, who, if they did not ſwear <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> unto
K. <hi>J.</hi> yet ſolemnly promis'd it? Read Father <hi>Alſop</hi>'s
Speech to the late King, in the Name, and at the
Head of a Body his Brethren, and you will be forc'd to ſay,
they are, if not falſe Swearers, yet egregious Lyars, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting
from their publick and declar'd Proteſtations,
which I think comes pretty near the Fault, others are (I
think unjuſtly) accus'd of. But I diſmiſs the <hi>Note-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:39246:12"/>
There remains now the Caſe of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and Mr. <hi>P.</hi> The
former's Greatneſs was alledg'd as ſufficient excuſe, why
he vouchſaf'd to make no Anſwer to his Accuſer; but
the <hi>Goliah</hi> look'd ſcornfully on little <hi>David,</hi> and made
no reckoning of him. He had leiſure to uncover the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs
of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> but none to hide his own; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile
them, but to commend himſelf. And for his greater
Honour to interweave the whole Hiſtory of the Times
and publick Tranſactions with his own; which (as I take
it) was too aſſuming and arrogant. Thus his Life ſwell'd
into a prodigious and intolerable length. 'Tis obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
that whoever ador'd him and embrac'd his Seutiments,
with what Laurels he was wont to adorn their Temples
as well as his own; but if any Man dar'd to gainſay
him, or refus'd to truckle unto his Dictates, they were
ſure to be Thunder-ſtruck by this <hi>J. O. M.</hi> For which
Reaſon the Ancient Fathers Infirmities were ſo impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
expos'd to the diſhonour of Chriſtianity. Though
we owe our Religion under God to their Zeal and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
For theſe and the like Reaſons, it was, that ſome
Men of his own Fraternity have rewarded him, as he
had ſerved others. Doubtleſs you have ſeen that Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the whole you will learn (as alſo by Mr. <hi>O</hi>'s.
and the Note-makers Writings) what liberty theſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient,
peaceable, mortify'd, and ſanctify'd Men: Theſe
are the uſual Characters they give one another) take in
ſpitefully reviling their Adverſaries, though in the main
of their own Perſwaſion; No wonder then if they treat
us as barbarouſly. And if you want another example of
this, I ſend you to <hi>the Confutation of Mr.</hi> Williams, <hi>by Mr.</hi>
Alſop, and to the <hi>Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> where no quarter
is given to theſe Gentlemen, who (eſpecially Father <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop)</hi>
are (as we ſpeak) <hi>handl'd without Mittens;</hi> But if a
Church of <hi>England</hi> Man meddles with any of 'em they
ſeem to be of the Humour of that lewd Souldier, who
excus'd himſelf thus, that the Commandment is <hi>thou ſhalt
not,</hi> but not, <hi>I ſhall not</hi>—The Author of the ſaid
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39246:13"/>
Pamphlet may venture to deliver many ſad Truths of Mr.
<hi>B.</hi> but the Rector muſt not. The ſumm is, and my deſign
was to note, that Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s. Greatneſs ought not to be his
Protection; nor did he truly deſerve that Epithet. A
Man ought not to be commended at adventures. All
that can be ſaid of him with reſpect to Greatneſs, is, that
He was a perſon of very good naturall Parts, but of no
Improvements proportionable to them. Thus much I
have to ſay on my own behalf for ſpeaking and writing as
I did, when juſt Ocaſion was offered me.</p>
            <p>The ſame Motive drew in Mr. <hi>P.</hi> he was a Paſsable
Man, and that's all that can be ſaid of him truly: but
to make an Hero of him, and to tell the World he ſhin'd
among us, <hi>tanquam inter Stellas Luna minores,</hi> to carry his
Character higher than it really deſerv'd, and for
want of Materials to gueſs at ſome excellencies, which
he was ſo far from meriting, that the contrary muſt
needs be allow'd againſt him, is an Artifice of advancing
the credit of a Party, which ought not to be endur'd,
and none but deſining Men will engage themſelves in.
What I took notice of, was his Marrying without the
Womans Parents conſent, and producing a <hi>Diploma</hi> or
Teſtimonial of taking his Degree at Cambridge.</p>
            <p>Hear then my Evidence. A Gentleman of my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
who knew him well, acquainted me with both above
Twenty years ago, and oft-times ſince, occaſionally in
Diſcourſe. When therefore I read his Life; I went im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly
to the Regiſter of the Claſs, where I found, <q>That
Mr. <hi>L.</hi> was accus'd, <hi>Aug.</hi> 15. 1650. for having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated
a Marriage between Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and one <hi>S. S.</hi>
Clandeſtinly and Irregularly, therefore the ſaid Mr. <hi>P.</hi>
and Mr. <hi>L.</hi> are appointed to appear again at the next
Meeting. <hi>Septemb. 12. ditto,</hi> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> is appointed to
bring in a Certificate under the hand of his own, and
his Wives Parents, teſtifying their conſent to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,
that the Claſs (a<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame time) hath receiv'd
ſatisfaction, and acquieſceth in the acknowledgment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39246:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> and Mr. <hi>L.</hi> concerning their irregular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
in the late Clandeſtine Marriage of Mr. <hi>P.</hi>
Then <hi>November 14. ditto</hi> Mr. <hi>P.</hi> brought in his Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate
concerning Parent conſent to the Marriage.</q> No
Man alive laying theſe things together, but would have
concluded the Marriage was made without the Conſent
of <hi>S.</hi> S's Parents, eſpecially when the other Report
prov'd true beyond all Controverſie. As for Mrs. <hi>P.</hi> and
<hi>R. M</hi>'s Teſtimony to the contrary, there is ſtill one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
in them; we are not told that Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s conſented to
the Marriage before its conſummation, and this is the
more to be ſuſpected, becauſe the Marriage was conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated
<hi>Clandeſtinely</hi> and <hi>Irregularly,</hi> under an Hedge in
an Ale-houſe, or without Banns asked, I know not which,
but I am ſure not by an Ordain'd Miniſter, contrary to
the Law of the Land. But why all this, if their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
had conſented before-hand? Beſides, it was Two
Months or ever Mr. <hi>P.</hi> produc'd a Certificate of Parents
conſent, which makes it probable <hi>his</hi> Parents conſented
not before the Marriage, but were drawn to it with dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty,
when there was no other remedy. Finally Mr.
<hi>P.</hi> acknowledg'd himſelf guilty of ſome Irregularity or
other, which is ſufficient to the general Deſign of my
Argument. However in the next place that Mr. <hi>P.</hi> took
no Degree in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> of <hi>C.</hi> proves true you ſee beyond
any Contradiction or Apology offer'd to the contrary.
And if my Relator was in the right in one Story, why
ſhould I queſtion the other? I avoid here ſpeaking open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
or further aggravating Mr. <hi>P</hi>'s fault; for I will not
dwell upon ſo foul a Miſcarriage, though one might take
the advantage here to expoſe both the guilty Party and
his Vindicator too. But I have utterly reſolv'd againſt
it, and ſo diſmiſs the Matter of Fact as now taken <hi>pro
confeſſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then you have an Inſtance of Mr. <hi>O</hi>'s dealing
with Arguments by halves, which fault he falls into al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
in every Page, and in ſome Pages more than once;
But we muſt bear with him in this, his Deſign being (as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39246:14"/>
to me ſeems) only to Write a Satyr and deride the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,
let the Points in Queſtion ſhift for themſelves as
they can. Much good may it do him. I am at his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
and when he has revil'd me as much as he's able,
I am perſwaded he'll never make the World believe; I
am either Fool, or Knave, or Impudent, or a <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi>
the Diſſenters themſelves (that know me) being
Judges: For to them I am content to ſurrender the Intereſts
of my Reputation. I will only ſpeak of one Paſſage in the
<hi>Vindication</hi> and ſo conclude. He acquaints his Reader p. 32.
that <hi>I give him the Character of a great Rogue.</hi> Really, if I
did ſo, I were no manner of way to be excuſed.
What I ſaid in <hi>R. R.</hi> p. 58. Was, <hi>That the Diſſenters have
themſelves own'd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting St. <hi>Chr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that if Mr.</hi> O. <hi>is indeed guilty of the
Crime laid againſt him, he is a great Rogue,</hi> and in the
Margin I declared the Expreſſion to be none of mine.
Now, Sir, I am content to be the Rogue my ſelf, if I
am guilty of calling him ſo. But if without any cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor
he has in this thing charged me falſly, and robb'd
me of my Reputation, among all thoſe that ſhall read
his Vindication, and not conſult my <hi>R. R.</hi> which I am
perſwaded one Reader of 100 will not do, then I leave
it to any Man's Judgment, whether he has not done
what in him lies to deſerve that Character which I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
did, nor will give him.</p>
            <p>Finally, I take leave to tell you, (I do it with
ſome Confidence) that there is ſcarce one Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph
(and they are numerous) but I could ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily
detect in it ſome material Defect or other,
and effectually anſwer it; but to what purpoſe?
When ſhall we have an end? It would have
been hard to undertake ſo particular a Reply,
without falling into hard words, which is the
thing I have carefully declin'd. I am not ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39246:14"/>
that I have given him any ill Language, or
Cauſe of Exaſperation, except haply it be in this
one thing, that I refuſe to ſcold with him.</p>
            <p>I hope both he and you will forgive me this wrong.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And remain yours,
<hi>T. G.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>April 8. 1699.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
